[Music]
so
[Applause]
[Music]
oh
[Applause]
[Music]
so
come on
[Music]
my name is apollo berlaza this is my
money life story in november 2015 my
wife and i met with a friend an emmanuel
life financial advisor and each of us
secured a policy young financial advisor
naming hindi
benta
manga policies next suggesting
[Music]
best at the same time my protection
unfortunately
august
[Music]
jung sakitko today i have fully
recovered from my heart condition and
now living a healthy and active
lifestyle last february 2021
komohanagamina is a punk policy for my
15 year old daughter we want to secure
her future as parents an insurance plan
is a great investment and one of the
best gifts we can give to our children
[Music]
maraming di silverado
will always be there to secure my family
my name is michelle herbaspar
this is my manual life story
it was in september 2016 when i took
steps to get an insurance policy that
will secure myself as well as my
immediate family
vegan financial advisor
explains
benefits to insurance planning
and it is one of the best decisions i've
made in my life no october 14 2020 i
proposed glenn a boyfriend of 10 years
at indiana
i said yes
after nyama proposed my fiance and i
started planning our wedding we made
sure that we were prepared financially
because we invested in a manual life
plan early on i am proud to say that we
had a debt-free wedding celebration
receivable three weeks before nakasel
namin
blessing talaga
if you are making a huge life decision
like getting married
napatmaruntayunclear financial
priorities
go on a budget plan in sempre stick with
it
bonus if my reliable partner got to
support you like manulife
my name is diana alvarado
this is my manual life story i was a
typical new graduate when i started my
job as a software engineer in one of the
most prestigious research and
development company here in cebu city
like any single newbie who receives her
paycheck i often spend it on anything i
want and i often find myself short for
the next payday it was my mom who
insisted that i buy a manulife insurance
plan then i was lucky to meet an agent
who took his time explaining the plan
details well he was patient and did not
take offense when i asked difficult
questions five years later my first
child was born
nathan he was perfect yet he came with
multiple congenital defects i found out
that my manual life insurance plan
covers maternity benefit for my child
the fund we received helped us in the
medical expenses
unfortunately
my baby did not survive his surgery
before he turned a year old
we feel like our manulife policy
helped us overcome a very difficult time
in our lives
in 2017 i gave birth to my second child
haley and in 2020 i gave birth to
another daughter
kayla
and i'm happy to share that both of my
daughters are healthy and so full of
life
life insurance is something you thought
you will never need
but when you need it you hoped you had
[Music]
all my mentoring journey began really if
we go back to the beginning from where i
was born in taiwan my parents were both
teachers in my elementary school there
was this like math challenge and then so
i actually won the prize that's the
first time i ever won something for math
so universal life i i decided to live in
residence canada even my you know social
circle and friends were very diverse it
made me realize that you can have a very
diverse
life experiences with a very diverse
group of people and sometimes you feel
like you kind of hide parts of yourself
but
you know the more authentic the more
open you are
people can surprise you it'll go away
well first impressions say wow he's a
really nice guy and not to lie
physically you know he was you know he
kind of took all the boxes
we talked about it for a while and you
know everything was aligning so we want
to get married having kids was
talked about that and and i think
once we you know look at the different
options you know we decided adoption is
where we want to go
we were there for the first ultrasound i
still have a picture
immediately after riley was born like we
were the one who kind of held her for
the first time and gave her her first
bottle of formula so yeah that was
that was
it's not just a job to me it's a it's a
family um and it's a journey that you
know continued to change and evolve it's
you know finding the right people to
support
to to kind of make that journey
together is it's what makes it
meaningful
just worry less go with the flow and
things work out the way it's supposed to
work out and don't underestimate the
power of a simple conversation it may
lead you somewhere else you don't expect
[Music]
while waiting for our program to start
may we invite everyone to share with us
what dei means to you
join the conversation by scanning the qr
code flashed on your screen
[Music]
so
hello and good evening everyone
we're grateful for your time this friday
night to celebrate and learn about
diversity and what we can do to build a
more equitable and inclusive society
now tonight's webinar is very important
for manulife because now more than ever
it is important to ensure that we help
create more safe spaces in our society
in workplaces in communities and in our
homes
whether you're a parent a sibling a
child a friend or a colleague each of us
has a role to play in ensuring that we
cultivate an environment where people
can be their true selves
and they can be heard valued and
respected
no matter their differences
we're living under vulnerable times
because of the pandemic
and though many of the changes has
brought us
being better allies to each other must
persist
now for our manual life true allyship is
the core of diversity equity and
inclusion
and it's simply the right thing to do
so to take stay true to our commitment
to make every day better for filipinos
and support all our communities
we join you as we come together
have meaningful conversations and learn
from one another
so we can help advance the change we
seek
thank you very much for joining us
tonight
together let's build a safer society for
all of us for many generations to come
now i'm delighted to turn you over to
our host
she's a distinguished writer journalist
editor at mega entertainment and a proud
member of the lgbtqia plus community
g3 san
thank you diego richard for that
introduction good evening and welcome
everyone to this evening's webinar
brought to you by a leading global life
insurance company manulife philippines
before we start i would like to take
this opportunity to thank manulife for
creating this event to serve as an
important platform for our speakers to
share their stories enlighten us through
their experiences and help us provide
more clarity and helpful insights when
we talk about diversity equity and
inclusion or dei
to talk about manufactu thrust
especially in building and sustaining
equality in places where we live work
and serve please welcome emmanuel's
chief marketing officer and the
philippine lead of manulife dei miss
melissa hanson
okay day three for the introduction and
a wonderful evening to everyone that is
spending their friday with us tonight
this is a very special night for us
because we will be talking about very
important topics of acceptance and
inclusion of understanding our
differences and opening ourselves up to
new perspectives so that we can debunk
some of the stereotypes and some of the
biases that foster discrimination so
tonight as g3 mentioned is all about dei
diversity equity and inclusion so you
might ask why we at manulife have
decided to host this webinar and devote
this evening to conversations about the
ei
manulife is a values-driven organization
and one of our core values is about
sharing our humanity and this means
embracing acknowledging and celebrating
our diversity as an organization
another one of our core values is doing
the right thing which is all about being
respectful always
and also doing right by our stakeholders
all the time
these values inspire us
drive us to build inclusive environments
where everyone can be their true whole
selves bring their whole selves to work
bring different ideas perspectives and
experiences to the table so that we can
grow together and we can make every day
better for each other
tonight our particular topic is allyship
and i'm often asked what i think it
means to be an ally what i often say
when i'm asked this question is that i
think being an ally is about listening
to each other about learning from each
other and seeking to understand each
other so that we can reach out
build bridges grow together and most
importantly lift each other up
at manulife being an ally to us is all
about our shared responsibility and our
shared accountability and proactively
building inclusive communities where
everyone can grow and thrive we believe
it's really important
to ask questions that allow us to
understand other people's needs and
perspectives their experiences even when
they're different from our own so it's
important to have conversations and ask
questions like whose voice and
perspective might we be missing out in
everyday conversations how do we amplify
these voices and these perspectives how
do we build safe spaces for one another
we need allies because it takes whole
village to make amazing things happen
and we have the whole village of
manulife philippines behind tonight's
event which we are presenting to you in
partnership with manulife proud or
professionals reaching out for unity and
diversity this is a group of employees
who help ensure that we build an
inclusive workplace for our lgbtq plus
colleagues and we are bringing this to
you in partnership with our global
women's alliance as well which is a
group that supports and encourages the
recruitment development and advancement
of women across the 70 markets where we
do business
as a global organization manulife
believes that diversity equity and
inclusion are key to driving growth and
transformation and this is why we have
worked dei into the way we work together
as a company and also the way we deliver
our products and services to our
customers so lgbtq plus domestic
partners can actually be designated as
beneficiaries for manulife policies
likewise for members of our team for our
colleagues our employees
domestic partners whether of the same
gender or otherwise can actually also be
designated as beneficiaries for our
various benefits so we try and work
really hard to foster a culture of
belonging because we believe that dei is
a key differentiator that can help us
gain a true understanding of each other
and allow us to make a meaningful and
positive impact when and where it
matters the most so once again thank you
for being with us tonight thank you for
being part of this very very important
conversation and enjoy the rest of the
evening
begin continue and amplify conversations
thank you mel pretty in pink indeed by
taking part in this webinar you are
already one step closer to becoming
better allies
before we introduce our speakers don't
forget to share your thoughts and
reactions on twitter by using the
hashtag safe spaces with manulife now
joining us this evening are four leading
advocates for equality as well as strong
and proud allies of diverse communities
in the country who may be
underrepresented
but whose unique identities and
perspectives contribute greatly to
social change we want to begin with a
woman who has received countless awards
and recognition not only for her acting
prowess but also for charitable works
throughout the years these include
forbes asia's heroes of philanthropy 30
outstanding altruists in asia pacific in
and one of tabler asia's 400 young
leaders shaping asia's future among many
others she is a true fearless filipina a
real-life dharna and very recently a
newlywed
my dear friend angel looks in arsene
[Music]
hello everyone at um thank you so much
for joining us tonight
next is a multi-awarded actor licensed
private pilot musician a person that
does not seem to age i told him earlier
that i've been watching him since
julian's son
and above all a loving and supportive
father
he was praised by many for being a
progressive parent let us welcome mr ian
venera hello everyone thank you g3 for
that wonderful introduction you know i
just realized
yeah nice
i i just realized that that sounds good
on paper you know because of that
introduction
another successful woman in our panel is
a lady who was chosen as one of only 10
unesco global champions of inclusive
education in 2020
our guest was born with down syndrome
but it did not stop her from achieving
her dreams in fact she graduated from a
regular high school as class
valedictorian and finished three college
degrees she is currently a preschool
assistant teacher and continues to be an
inspiration to many filipinos everyone
let's welcome miss brinake
[Music]
hello everyone
good evening
next is the founder and chairperson of
the youth for mental health coalition
inc he is a medical director and a
mental health advocate to provide us
expert advice and important mental
health insights is dr rj nagiot
hello everybody
thank you everyone for joining us
tonight icebreaker
to start things in a happy light shall
we okay
at the top of your head what is one word
that best describes your lessons and
experiences
during the pandemic i want to start with
papa ian
yes g3
one word to describe your experiences
uh
during the pandemic it's just basking in
silence silence from
um from chaos
silence very peaceful what about you gel
um
[Music]
definitely slowed us down uh it gave us
time a lot of time actually to reflect
on what really matters to but and i know
sometimes it feels like
it's
but to remain hopeful and
take inspiration uh knowing this too
shall pass
very true what about you brina what's
your one word
um
perseverance all right dr rj
i know acceptance
uncertainties came pandemic and of
course there are a lot of uh acceptance
that we need to do uh in terms of the
things that we can change on the things
that we have lost
so acceptance is something that we need
to also learn
my one word would be survival i want to
thank everyone for being here and the
fact that we are all here means we are
champions of surviving this pandemic has
forced us to slow down and reflect like
what angel said on what truly matters
great time to talk about how you started
with your advocacies brina i want to
start with you you have accomplished so
much at such a young age
when did you and your family learn about
your diagnosis and how has it impacted
your life growing up
i was born with down syndrome
when i was still a tiny baby a doctor
told my parents that i will not live
long
because my condition was really very bad
i was in a very bad shape
but
my parents refused to believe the doctor
instead they played hard and they did
everything they could so that i live
long
today i am still alive and i'm already
25 years old
so you see
since i was a little child it had been a
struggle for me
life was so difficult growing up
that sometimes i thought i will already
die early
i thank god for keeping me alive until
today
i think
my family my doctors
and my favorite best for taking care of
me
and i know that god's grace i will live
long
amen by god's grace you will live long
that's what i talk about when i say
survival you finished three university
courses i couldn't even survive with
just one how did you do that that's
amazing and i mean looking motivation
more to work hard in school and to keep
on learning
my motivation is my own desire to
achieve despite my disability i want to
inspire parents and other children with
disabilities
and there is hope
that i can achieve for as long as i
believe in myself
and because i believe that god will help
me
yes god helps us all sometimes you
really don't need to have to look far to
find inspiration gel
here is a well-known champion of many
causes including women empowerment
jailback
when did the passion start and when did
it get stronger
thank you for that wonderful question
well
actually
i never presented myself with the
champion of
of different causes
inspiring
and um actually i can't uh i can't
really pinpoint
calendar like this
ever since i was young i'd always found
myself rooting for the underdogs and
they really dislike bullies
humans and the young
social beings diba
i think we're wired to feel each other's
pain
especially
it's a crime against humanity
even in the characters that you played
on screen it showed that you were a
strong woman superhero lahat and
everything
favorite character more than a playmo is
monica of the legal wife
that was very powerful for me but for
you what is your
character that you really really admire
the most that you played
well thank you
i don't know i've
i have always been attracted to playing
rules that are
empowering
it's never too late to do the right
thing so my hope i like i like doing uh
characters
that's true that's true a character that
plays that provides hope is a character
to remember
papa ian you were recently lauded by
many for being a proud
father to dibs who is a proud member of
the lya class community
para
what does it mean to be a responsible
and supportive parent
um
for me
honestly
i don't think it has anything to do with
anything
um
the things uh when when she told me
about it and um
yeah it's it's it's so casual and i
don't see her as uh
yeah i see her as a as a human being
and she sees herself as that too not not
just uh
apart a member of a particular group or
of any group because it's like we're
trying to
about i i i love that we have these
discussions because
we're trying to um get rid of boxes we
don't want to be put in a box and we
also don't want to put ourselves in
boxes and categorize and we don't want
to put others in boxes so i think it
starts with ourselves and i i think of
course no it has
it had served its utility in the past
when we we categorize things and we
it's like a primordial tribalist a kind
of tribalism so we identify with groups
we group ourselves into clusters but
yeah it's really important um especially
now to
to not put ourselves into
certain categories because
i think
we have the capacity now uh
we've learned so much from history we
have the capacity as human beings to
expand our consciousness and to
um
to embrace that oneness and uh
to see with fresh eyes the beauty of uh
the uniqueness of these people of
everyone
in junior
when we
when we identify with a certain group
sometimes we have a tendency to alienate
others
and
um
i mean sometimes it goes as far as to uh
it divides people sometimes it becomes
women versus men sometimes it becomes
straight man versus game and sometimes
it becomes this versus that it's so
dualistic and i i think
we have the capacity now to really
transcend that
and uh progress uh forward so with deeds
it was
nothing it wasn't as super casual and um
nothing it's not a big issue it's like
saying i like wearing yellow socks okay
unique and completely the same i
understand what you are saying
i mean like all coming out stories are
very important they're very personal i
wish
there will come a day when coming out
stories are no longer necessary but i
want to ask you
how did this come out to you
one day she was teary-eyed and she said
dad can i talk to you i said sure sit
down and she said
i like girls
and i said
yeah me too i like girls too no girls
are awesome and she she was laughing and
i was laughing
and
she said so it's okay i said yes just
never ever be apologetic about it not to
anyone not even to me
because that's your
i mean
a person's capacity to love and
and a capacity a person's capacity to
feel pain has nothing to do with their
sexual preferences it's the same as has
nothing to do with their skin color or
where they were born
i mean it's so irrelevant and it's
for me
okay
thanks for informing me but it's it's
really
irrelevant
so um she was really happy about it of
course of course yeah not all parents
react that way that's very cool actually
very accepting and embracing
um at the onset i want to share my own
coming out story i didn't actually have
a coming out story because you know
growing up i it was pretty obvious i
mean like my parents didn't have to ask
me or i didn't have to come out at the
dinner table or anything like that i was
very effeminate growing up my coming out
story came later on in life because you
know i started to transition at 16 years
old
and i was really wondering why do i feel
this way because you know i i studied an
exclusive school for boys and i was like
more than anything i just feel so
different from them and then when i
realized who i was
i started to live life comfortably as a
woman my coming up story was very
different it was when i came out as a
trans woman because for you
to be
to feel different all your life and
suddenly you come into a mold where
people accept you as a woman
then finally coming out with your truth
that i am not cisgender i am transgender
then you subject yourself to a lot of
scrutiny a lot of rejection then that's
when i needed courage to actually come
out as a trans woman so that was
officially my coming out story i didn't
come out as a gay boy i didn't come out
as a woman i came out as a trans woman
it was a very fashionable coming out
thing because it was through a magazine
editorial
and i want to thank you know the
magazine for that but you know that was
my coming out story
and it's true what papa ian said having
a supportive environment matters the
laga i want to ask dr rj why do you
think dei conversations are important
some mental health at well being nathan
well of course the eye is very important
that stigma discrimination and the
stereotypes that come with it uh all
create barriers
not only confronts
our identities as individuals but it
also challenges the existing power
imbalances
economic and even uh other
power imbalance balances
and of course all of these create
unnecessary non-existent walls and
division among people and pogba
i remember a very uh close friend tell
me when you come out it's not just
coming out but it's also coming home
when we talk about mental health and
sometimes human social stigma human
stereotypes
can come into us
internalize and that's what you call
self-stigma so human
negative the master types
negative connotations a specific group
they tend to become self-fulfilling
prophecies
important telegram addresses stigma
because it's directly linked to our
mental well-being
that's true that's true i like the word
other link i said that's something that
we should watch out for and something
that we should not do because about the
essence of every human being is you know
the same components recently we
witnessed a historic success in the
tokyo 2020 olympics where manulife's
very own ambassador hitalin diaz bagged
the very first olympic gold medal for
the philippines brina you also
represented the country by being one of
only 10 special olympics sergeant
shriver international
global messengers you are also
one of only 10 united nations unesco
global champions of inclusive education
how did you feel when they chose you to
be their spokesperson
i was very happy when i was chosen as
one of only 10 special olympics
children's swiper international global
messengers from all over the world
i travel around the world to inspire
people and promote courage
hope acceptance and dignity of people
with intellectual disabilities
the united nations forced me as one of
only 10 unesco global champions for
inclusive education this is my advocacy
they said that i am a good example
myself
having graduated college because of
occlusion
i have down syndrome and because my iq
was very low
it's psychologist to my parents that i
may not even finish grade school
but
i institute i worked w hard
i attended very good at schools not
special schools
i graduated from college
i survived the bullies
they called me ugly and stupid
i proud to be chosen as
united nations unesco global example for
inclusive education
because i am the only one who is a bwd
and i am the only one from asia
the other nine examples are doctors
educators and government officials from
other parts of the world
it's amazing i mean all your
achievements are so amazing to us you
are also a teacher have you always
wanted to teach brina and why
yes i always wanted to be a teacher
so that i can help children with
intellectual disabilities like me i am a
proud assistant teacher at pian in the
greatest school of paranaque
where i graduated from preschool but i
still dream of having my own school and
only equal sister someday
your own school we are going to wait for
that you know this year's pool of
philippine olympians have broken
stereotypes as women brought home medals
in stereotypically male dominated sports
that are such weightlifting and boxing
and male athletes represented the
country in sports like gymnastics it
sparked an important conversation about
typecasting and encouraging people that
they can excel at anything regardless of
their gender
pares
what were some of the stereotypes or
labels that you had to overcome or prove
wrong and i want to start this
conversation by
picking my own example i mean like when
you are a trans woman you only go two
ways it's either
you work in a salon or you join beauty
pageants you know i don't have a talent
in either i have no aspirations but you
know like growing up a trans woman i've
always wanted to become a journalist and
today i am the first
trans woman editor of any magazine in
the philippines and i just want to say
that you know just because people box
you in certain areas
beauty parlor
beauty pageant
it doesn't have to discourage you from
occupying spaces other than those fields
of course
we have a lot of beautiful trans women
that have won international beauty
pageants and of course we have a lot of
artists in
working in the salons but it shouldn't
stop us from occupying spaces other than
those
typically parents who want their
children to follow in their footsteps
career-wise in your case did you
encourage your kids to also be in show
business
[Music]
in my case actually i discouraged them
by bringing them to taping
to
for for them to see that uh you know uh
to to see beyond the magic of uh
of television of movies say so they can
see i it's pretty boring
all you do here is wait and
uh chasmisa and kolita
i have no problems if they want to if
they find it interesting
i also don't want to deprive them of
their own journey
i'm going to
as a parent of course i'm going to act
like a padrino
i'm going to call my friends
you know
and um
i don't think it's good for them really
that's why i i'd like them to uh
to uh carve their own path
and um just like uh myself it's it's a
source of my confidence also
that
i know i have no padrino in showbiz i
don't come from a family of showbiz
when when is that wake us you know you
have to
you know you have to do your homework
you you have to be nice to people you
have to do your job well it's uh you
know you know it's based on competence
not based on the people you know
so
and i think it's very important for any
person to
to gain confidence from that
um knowing that
you know in
responsible society
so that's that's one of the reasons
but if they really want to uh it's okay
also
but of course he did is start off in the
performing arts yabara she is also music
so you have that in common so i assume
like at home you also jam thereby you
share your talents to each other
sessions
you belong to me is this is an old old
song yeah can we hear parts today
um india already wait you're already
okay um so yeah i'm gonna take off my
nose so i don't hear the delay here's a
small sample
[Music]
see the pyramids along the line
watch the sunrise sonotropic kind
just remember darling
you belong to me
[Music]
see the marketplace and old algiers
send me photographs and souvenirs
just remember when a dream appears
you belong to me
i'll be so long without you
[Music]
maybe you'll be lonesome too
fly the ocean in a silver plain
see the jungle when it's wet with rain
[Music]
just
remember home again
[Music]
the guy from lighthouse had a very
beautiful version of that i don't
remember his name but yes that's such a
familiar
song
great talent
if you could have one of darna's super
powers in real life
what would it be
the
[Music]
that's true that's true champagne apart
from playing dharna you've played very
throughout your career what should you
know women take too hard
ah
what's real and who is real
that's true it's hard to find something
real in an industry like ours
living in a predominantly conservative
country where many people still label
and put them into boxes
what do you think filipinos need to
understand better about our communities
i want to start again with brina what do
they need to understand better about
persons or children with disabilities
at least that all children with
intellectual disabilities like me
miss out with untraditional love and
that people accept us for what we are
i hope
for total acceptance and inclusion in
schools and in society
i wish that people accept us for what we
are
respect us
and with us with dignity
please do not call us names like stupid
man is weird or ugly
because it hurts our feelings
please do not bully us
please believe in us
we can do more and be more
that's true that's true sometimes
children kids can be so mean and i think
it's going to start with parents how you
teach your children to accept people
with differences who are different from
you who might you know seem to be
different from who you are and of course
i also want to share you know what
society needs to better understand about
the lgbtqia plus community as a
representative here i mean i think the
bottom line is you know we share the
same humanity no matter you know how
different you feel we are from you no
matter how you try to make us invisible
just because you know we sometimes we
make you feel uncomfortable it's just
you know the basic you know knowledge of
you know us all being human beings
at the very core of every person is you
know
a human being very similar from you so
that's just really what i want people to
understand about our community you know
that we may you know love differently
we may look differently but in the core
of all of us is really the same same
humanity
instances
about her own
encounters of discrimination
um
there was a time like i said she's very
athletic and
she's a good football player stopper and
there was a time as a school
that
she wasn't allowed during pe to play uh
football with the boys because the girls
had a different activity and she was
like no it's unfair blah blah blah blah
blah so she's really furious about it
and um
i told her uh
to
to do
something to talk to her teacher or
you know act responsibly and manage her
temper
and you know as a father i i of course i
want to make my child uh safe pero more
than that i want them to be strong i
want to prepare them because there are
so many
um they will have to slay so many
dragons in their lives
and um i cannot be there to protect them
all the time so they need to
be assertive they need to stand up for
themselves
and learn
how to manage uh
adversity responsibly
and so i i told her to deal with it on
her own
um
and
yeah i i think that's that's that's an
important
thing to teach our children also to be
responsible
how they handle situations but they're
responsible for their thoughts their
actions their words uh their emotions
and union because maraming
at some point in in their life they
would probably encounter someone who's
racist against filipinos what do we do
we do do we protect them
our whole lives no we make we make them
we make sure that uh strong character
and alumni
handle
and we make sure that their self-respect
is not based on how others see them
they're not dependent on external
validation
and you know basis for self-respect
foundation
that's true that's true we equip our
children for the tools that they need
you know to survive in this life because
we won't always be there for them
for jail the man they're often cliches
about what a successful woman is it's
like you know the timelines that they
need to follow or the rules that they
need to assume
what makes a woman truly successful
um
for me a woman is really successful if
she's uh
capable of choosing her own path
your success is having um
the freedom to follow your heart
impose gender roles in
and that is the definition of success
a very very important issue in today's
climate is mental health the bab all of
us you know we have gone through that
throughout the pandemic why do you think
some filipinos is very very
uncomfortable about talking about mental
health
well a lot of reasons actually you know
but the first reason very common for me
is uh of course
access your manga to the right services
or the right information about mental
health because usually
two concepts like depression anxiety
suicide but usually mental illnesses but
we rarely talk about mental health in
the positive lens so okay recognizing
that mental health is a spectrum so uh
regardless where you are in the spectrum
mental interventions that should be
given to you
uh mental health condition then usually
you know a reason why people don't talk
about it second is of course in social
stigma
as weak as unproductive
among misconceptions and then lastly
for wellness of our communities
and that's why during the pandemic uh
topics like self-compassion are very
important
hindi realistic
um
as compared to how we will treat other
people so okay
as we would be kind to other people
that's actually a very great insight
because we see ourselves differently
sometimes we're more judgmental about
ourselves and you know i mean yes so
anima nothing going to make a positive
difference in improving community
challenges related to women
persons with disability the lgbtqia plus
community and other marginalized sectors
doc
well i think we have to recognize first
that all of the struggles that we face
are somehow interrelated to each other
intersectionality of issues okay so for
example when we were starting the youth
for mental health coalition
are coming from the lgbt community and
they recognize them in the same young
stigma in discrimination
once we recognize
issues coming up in pakistan i think
that's something that we need to um that
we can actually uh do something about no
lunapan specific programs and policies
and uh when we craft uh for example our
policies say for example the covenanting
response
in the
because
if we want to make the i happen we have
to be deliberate about it it cannot be
an afterthought
so um and of course
and strategize how we would correct the
imbalances
of
when it comes to political and even
economic issues and something
incorporate for us know as allies it's
important for us to continue listening
to them because say i think that empathy
is is like a muscle no so it grows and
exercise it and um i think in coding for
us to
uh
smuggling malacca
impact
towards these groups important that we
also learn their stories and their pain
points and some sometimes those pain
points cannot be communicated
in the first contacts
with the different sectors that we try
to actually work
with empathy as a muscle so we have to
exercise
to our audience if you have questions
for our speakers piece feel free to
ask them in our q a box at the bottom of
your screen we will answer them later
during the q and a session i want to
talk about purpose now we i want to know
naman ang inspiration yo let's start
with you papa ian
tina inspires
my children because of of all the roles
that i play
i think um
being a father is definitely my my
favorite role and it um
well it makes my life meaningful
what about you gel who inspires you or
what inspires
us
um
who inspires you
well for me one of the specific
individuals
in in the past few years
at times that i got disappointed
for example
[Applause]
that's true that's true initiative you
know takes a great part in that what
about you brina who
inspires you
my inspiration is my whole family
they support me and love me
unconditionally
my daddio is also a bwd like me
because he has aware and incredible
disease
we
inspire each other
he's my best friend number one
he is your best friend your daddy is
your best friend how do families and
schools play a major role in normalizing
dei brina
family is very important because they
will defend you against bullies
a family will help you with the problems
family will accept you
for who you are
that's true your family is the first to
accept you
go in to make a big impact in the long
run like ensuring parents raise their
children more confident about themselves
and support people who are considered
different
now i think it's really important to
start with ourselves because we can
be
open to other perspectives if we
ourselves are not open to it
and um
yeah the sense of responsibility
we have to be also
so really not and uh responsible when it
comes to
not putting people in boxes
um
being open to different ideas
to uh
discussions
and
uh
example
and hopefully
uh
to stand up more for themselves
well i firmly believe that education
plays an
let's allow ourselves to be a refuge
let's create a safe place for everyone
will represent that
of course that includes men in the
bathroom and how can they stand up for
equality and defy unfair expectations
brought about by the macho culture jail
oh
[Laughter]
you know you know um uh
i i come from a
family of strong women from my lawless
to my mother to my
wife to my daughter
[Laughter]
thank you
by our words or actions
then call up the perpetrator
um i'd like to encourage everyone just
to know like what i said earlier just to
take up their own space i mean your
talents your skill level your
competencies don't have to you know
correspond to the
the things that you know are assigned to
you or whatever
you know yourself better than anyone
else and whatever it is your competence
level is go on in balance mode and
that's where you should shine and that's
where you should exert yourself
you know guys before we proceed to the q
a we'd like to first acknowledge the
presence of our friends from the media i
want to acknowledge our friends from the
philippines star manila times daily
tribune u dot ph metro dot style one in
manila click the city wonder mag corner
magazine boy rocket
lifestyle portal lionheart tv and trend
hotspot all right
now let's bring back all our guests on
our screen are you ready to answer the
questions in our q and a box
are you ready guys
okay so we want to start with jail many
young girls today are on social media
and the thrill of being a celebrity can
be very tempting i know advice
how can they grow up an empowered woman
like if you are popular on social media
they equate it to worth they equate it
to importance so what about you gel how
can you grow up
an empowered woman and what is the
advice that you can give to all of these
young ladies
[Music]
so i can be a lot closer to my teenage
kids
but don't see me as a cool dad
um
it's hard to give
specific advice to someone
but
but uh i i i'll just share how i am with
my kids
from
okay i wanna go to brina now what do you
do to recharge yourself man what are
your favorite hobbies and activities
hello hello can you hear me g3 yes i can
hear you now but
brina is going to talk first
i think you are on mute brina
that's an exercise every day to be
physically fit
i do research puzzles every day because
it helps me learn more words
and know the meanings
okay i want to go back to papa ian what
can you do to become a cool dad
uh as i was saying um i encourage my
kids to to know not just the good side
but also learn from my strengths and my
weaknesses
and my i mean we all have flaws so they
i want them to see those flaws
okay hear me yes i can hear you now
okay let me jump right back into brina
to ask her what her favorite song to
dance to is
i love to dance to hip hop
i love to dance to hip hop dance music
hip hop dancing
hip hop i'm going to ask dr rj in terms
of mental health how do you know if you
need to ask for
professional help already
sometimes
depression comes
you know we we battle with bouts of
sadness and depression and you know at
church they call it languishing because
of the time that we stayed indoors and
you know
been confined to the spaces that are you
know within the four walls of our homes
[Laughter]
and you don't necessarily have to have a
mental health diagnosis for
is
so the first d is what we call this
function
for example you're
there's a disconnect between your
external environment and your internal
emotional state so disconnect then
probably
professional support and then a fourth
is since we're talking about um mental
health
topic and suicide cannot be shied away
from no self-harm
or harming other people then probably
it's a sign that you need to seek
professional help already and then
um
three weeks dividing sadness
usually
emotions
and you can't explain it then usually
it's a sign that you need to go to a
professional so young 5d saiyan are just
the basics
professional you would undergo several a
psychological and even um a
psychological interview para passart and
telegonilla what your diagnosis is
dysfunction deviance distress what's the
fourth be you didn't mention the
danger
and the last one is duration duration
okay so do you need to have all those
five days to call a professional or just
one or
two or three of all all of you
it's always best to go early to a
psychiatrist or a psychologist
available
okay so we go to another d dynamics um
somebody wants to know papaya and what
your family dynamics are
do you think
decision to come out to you because of
you know how you relate to your family
what makes a
family a safe space to come out for any
childhood
what
in your family dynamics made it very
easy for dates to come out to you
um
we spent so much time together and and
we're really really close
and yeah they see not just the good side
but the bad side they they're
they know me
uh more than anyone so
ganondenz i think it's really important
that they feel uh
a sense of security
that they're uh they're loved
unconditionally
and that they're not being judged based
on
how they on our own criteria or our own
expectations
um that they're free to uh
to think for themselves and that they're
free to be who they want to be
and i think that that plays a big role
in them being comfortable to
to
come out
exactly parenting for you the question
here for me is it important for a queer
person to define or find out where in
the lgbtqia plus spectrum they fall
under and how can i ask for someone's
pronouns respectfully
like i said earlier
like in i grew up in the 90s and in the
90s the terms were not clearly defined
yet so you know growing up in atheneo i
was like in a boys school so feeling
good
i was gay because what happened among
clear defined terms
i didn't know i was trans so i think if
you are a person growing up and you
don't know who you are i think it's you
know it's okay to take your time i mean
the spectrum now is broader more than
ever
lgbt
the spectrum is so broad the by you all
of us fall into that spectrum so i think
when you you know question who you are
and when you start to realize who you
are
it's important to take your time so you
know where you belong in the spectrum
there's really no pressure and you know
allowing yourself to learn who you
really are so that's really you know the
advice that i would give is just to take
your time and you talk to people who
have you know probably
gone through the same path as you it's
very important that you talk to your
parents also for guidance and stuff like
that and with regards to pronouns my
pronouns are she her hers
um
generally speaking what people
express themselves at what they look as
that's generally the pronouns that they
want to be used
if they express themselves as female
then use the pronoun she her hers if
they express himself as male then he
him his but it's always polite and safe
to ask first you know you know in in the
church that i go to when the pastor
prays for me he asks me what pronouns
are you comfortable with and then i
answer sometimes
so i think
generally speaking what they the gender
expression is that is the pronouns that
you should use but it's always safe to
ask first i'm going to ask gel again
this is a question from our audience
what do you think is the importance of
using your platform to drive important
causes and advocacy because you have a
very very large following
you are one of the most followed and
influential filipinas um on social media
so how do you use that platform
for a responsible way to you know spread
your message of hope to everyone
um
social media plays a
very crucial role because in shaping the
minds of the younger generation say so
me i try my best to
use the platform my platform in sharing
what i think is helpful and beneficial
for example uh on twitter account
is it's one for three red angel
one for three because i love you red
indian
one for three cha has a one for three
casing hotline and red cross and
uh
but in case of emergency
so they can easily ask for help
and
also the fastest week i said to reach
out to people and to uh to raise
awareness about our causes our
advocacies is online
saying that but i want to thank also the
red cross for the good work that they've
been doing in the pandemic you know we
you know i've gone to the red cross with
you at some point and you know they're
doing an excellent job this is another
question for me it says how important is
representation in the workplace or in
media
i mean like growing up
people like me that if ever maybe home
people like me
they're always portrayed in the
teleseries and they're on the in the
movies with charles nasa parlor
i have yet to watch a very accurate
representation of trans women on screen
or in media that's why you know i try to
be very visible in the spaces that i
occupy but if ever there is a young
person
that wants to be a journalist that wants
to be a writer that's one that wants to
work behind the screen then they
probably have somebody to look up to
cause
i think really now is the time to you
know blaze a trail i don't mind that i
didn't have you know representation
growing up
but it means you know it just gives us
you know more time to blaze a trail it
gives us an opportunity to blaze a trail
i want to ask the doc rj when
experiencing emotional distress
how do you clear your heads
well
starts in guru you have to decrease the
stibuli now because i mean
it can become overwhelming for some
people so an overwhelming capacity to
cope with with several stressors so
important
um
but at the same time we also need to
accept the idea that we cannot
completely clear our head space right
because
but it's just a matter of managing those
thoughts and compartmentalizing them
depending on readiness what to act on
them so
aside from i know accepting and of
course decreasing the level of stimuli
you might want to look for a way for you
to release those emotions now so it can
be through art it can be through word
journal or you can also
release it through physical exercise
and then of course we have to also
accept that
um
we can't just embrace the positive
emotions and leave out the negative ones
it's a normal dream for us as as human
beings to have positive and negative
emotions and means
a situation
sobering
it's normal for you to feel
uh bad no it's it's okay for you to feel
frustrated to be angry so the more i
said that we shelve our emotions the
more likely silent matagal so
[Music]
accept your emotions embrace your
feelings i think
for everyone what makes you proud of
being an ally because
like you know a lot of people say oh i'm
an lgbt ally i'm an ally i'm an ally
what an ally means to me really and this
is my definition of being an island it
doesn't mean you know that you have gay
friends or you have gay relatives
children parents whatever that makes you
an ally for me that's not an ally an
ally for me is somebody who will not
stop fighting until their rights are
equal to yours
being an ally for me the true definition
is really when you do not stop until the
rights of others are equal to yours that
is an ally for me what guys makes you
proud of being an ally and i want to
start with brina an ally to you know
people that are in the marginalized
communities what
word defines you as an ally
that i have
quite a number of achievements despite
my disability
but i really worked very hard
that you pretty hard
i mean like we really really rely on our
abilities you know to be able to relate
to people what about you gel what makes
you proud of being an ally
um
you know you know to be an ally of a
community driven by love is an it's an
honor
if you feel one with them in their
struggles
priceless
that's true what about you papa ian what
makes you proud of being not just a
father but an ally to the community
um
is i think the fact that
i'm always willing to be supportive uh
and to fight oppression against women
children the elderly it doesn't matter
oppression happens to everyone and not
only that but you need to encourage
people
okay
to start with myself and hope and
hopefully
start with yourself okay so we want to
move on to dr rj what makes you proud of
becoming an ally is being an ally
well if you wouldn't know uh listen to
the greeks ferocious having different
types of love and what they say the
highest form of love is what we call
agape because it extends beyond you know
beyond your immediate circle
proud to be an ally
[Music]
[Applause]
so i think it's important for us to
recognize that as allies
okay so i think we still have a lot of
great questions from our audience but
unfortunately this time the all the time
we have for this evening i want to check
there's one question for each that we
want to ask so two questions from the
audience
first um i want to start with angel
what's your advice to young girls who
are afraid to speak up because
too strong for a girl
[Music]
did you hear the question gel
who's strong for our girl
i think
is
[Laughter]
i guess on that note we're going to ask
for our final
for our fan list for the final words i
want to start with brina
what are your final words in making
people understand you know
our community how you know they can
make every day better
for themselves and the community what
are your final words brina
people need intellectual
disabilities like me
also human beings
and i want to ask
yes go ahead you have something to add
people with intellectual disabilities
like me
please leave us because we can do more
and be more
if only you give us the chance
we can do more and be more given the
chance what a beautiful final message
what about you doc rj are any final
words for
people who are watching us tonight
well
i'll relate it to mental health
as individuals as a group
we have to extend
patience extra kindness
um
your millions of fans followers and
admirers what are your final words for
tonight as an ally as a you know proud
father of people for somebody in the
community what are your final words for
us
um
uh respect
uh
love
compassion
and um we're all here as temporary
visitors
so it's really really important that we
coexist in the more most harmonious way
possible
and um it starts with ourselves
for her final words for tonight you know
the people that are listening and
watching us what can you say to them
well um
always do what's right and
everything's gonna be all right
i'll do what is right i think you know
in that basic sense
tonight i learned that you know empathy
is a muscle and i think when you learn
so we have i know empathy
that is what makes us different that is
what you know sets us apart so i think
that when you put yourself in the
positions of others
whether it be you know they are
disabled or in the lgbtqia community or
whatever marginalized sector there is in
the community if you put yourself in
that position then you begin to
understand you know how they need to be
treated how they need to feel and i
guess as a final word you know just
practice empathy you know everyone is
going there is a purpose to why all of
us are going through the same thing at
the exact same time the whole world is
going through the same thing
i think there is a reason for us to you
know go through all of these things
together
at the same time and you know it just
brings us to a place of empathy towards
others you know there have been a lot of
movements throughout the past month
throughout the past year if you're
really just fighting for equality you
know just be fighting for your place and
society and this is you know it comes at
the heels of something that is
potentially very dangerous to humanity
but again you know it forces us to look
deeper it forces us to realize you know
the things that we have and the you know
it just makes us realize that we are
ultimately connected to one another we
are gathered to one another and so that
connection should be enough to tell you
that you know whatever you do affects
even you know the farthest person from
you in terms of geography
that is what the pandemic taught us we
are all connected chaos theory whatever
but we are all connected and that
connection should give us empathy
towards each other so yo young final
word call for tonight and in closing i
just want to say maraming
speakers for taking the time out of your
friday night so we can all learn how to
become better allies
thank you also to manulife for being an
organization that supports diverse
communities not just
starting meaningful conversations like
this
but also in practice from honoring
domestic lgbtqia partners as
beneficiaries
to products that cater to gender
inclusive needs and critical illness
coverage that includes permanent
disabilities you have really shown us
that you are continuously learning and
taking action to ensure that you are
doing the right thing the dei way
it all starts with us listening
conversing and expanding our audience so
we can reach and teach more filipinos
about values that help
us build a more inclusive world
please continue this important
conversation on twitter
by using the hashtag safe spaces with
manulife make sure to like and follow
manulife philippine social media pages
for the latest updates we'd like to hear
your feedback on this evening's webinar
scan the qr code on screen and answer
our two minute survey it has been a
pleasure hosting for you i am g3 san
diego my pronouns are she her hers
remember that by creating safer spaces
that allow us to rethink and debunk
stereotypes
we share our humanity we can help build
an inclusive world and make every day
better thank you and say
stay safe everyone
bye guys
[Music]
oh my
journey begin really if we go back to
the beginning from where i was born in
taiwan my parents were both teachers in
my elementary school there was this like
math challenge and then so i actually
won the prize that's the first time i
ever won something
for that so universal life i i decided
to live in residence canada even like
you know social circle and friends were
very diverse it made me realize that you
can have a very diverse life experiences
with a very diverse group of people and
sometimes you feel like you kind of hide
parts of yourself
but
you know the more authentic the more
open you are
people can surprise you in a good way
well first impressions like wow he's a
really nice guy and not to lie
physically you know he was you know he
kind of took all the boxes
we talked about it for a while and you
know everything was aligning so we want
to get married
having kids was
talked about that and and i think
once we you know look at the different
options you know we decided adoption is
where we want to go we were there for
the first ultrasound i still had a
picture
immediately after riley was born like we
were the one who kind of held her for
the first time and gave her her first um
bottle of formula so yeah that was
that was
it's not just a job to me it's a it's a
family um and it's a journey that you
know continue to change and evolve and
it's you know finding the right people
to support um to to kind of make that
journey
uh together is it's what makes it
meaningful
just worry less go with the flow and
things work out the way it's supposed to
work out and don't underestimate the
power of a simple conversation it may
lead to somewhere else you don't expect
[Music]
my name is apollo berlaza this is my
money life story in november 2015 my
wife and i met with a friend a manual
life financial advisor and each of us
secured a policy young financial advisor
naming hindi
ben tahan among the policies
suggested
[Music]
at the same time my protection
unfortunately
august 2019 the following day
and i ask him
[Music]
today i have fully recovered from my
heart condition and now living a healthy
and active lifestyle last february 2021
komohanagamina is a fun policy for my 15
year old daughter we want to secure her
future as parents an insurance plan is a
great investment and one of the best
gifts we can give to our children
[Music]
life will always be there to secure my
family
my name is michel herbaspar
this is my manual life story
it was in september 2016 when i took
steps to get an insurance policy that
will secure myself as well as my
immediate family
vegan financial
and it is one of the best decisions i've
made in my life on october 14 2020 i
proposed
glenn a boyfriend of 10 years at indiana
easter i said yes
afternoon my proposed my fiancee and i
started planning our wedding we made
sure that we were prepared financially
because we invested in a manual life
plan early on i am proud to say that we
had a debt-free wedding celebration
received
out from manulife three weeks before
nakasel namin
if you're making a huge life decision
like getting married
napatma financial priorities
go on a budget plan in sempre stick with
it
bonus if my reliable partner got to
support you like manulife
my name is diana alvarado
this is my manual life story i was a
typical new graduate when i started my
job as a software engineer in one of the
most prestigious research and
development company here in cebu city
like any single newbie who receives her
paycheck i often spend it on anything i
want and i often find myself short for
the next payday it was my mom who
insisted that i buy a manulife insurance
plan then i was lucky to meet an agent
who took his time explaining the plan
details well he was patient and did not
take offense when i asked difficult
questions five years later my first
child was born
nathan he was perfect yet he came with
multiple congenital defects i found out
that my manual life insurance plan
covers maternity benefit for my child
the fund we received helped us in the
medical expenses
unfortunately
my baby did not survive his surgery
before he turned a year old
we feel like our manulife policy
helped us overcome a very difficult time
in our lives
in 2017 i gave birth to my second child
haley
and in 2020 i gave birth to another
daughter
kayla
and i'm happy to share that both of my
daughters are healthy and so full of
life
life insurance is something you thought
you will never need
but when you need it you hoped you had
[Music]
[Applause]
oh
[Music]
uh
come on
[Music]
you